{"tossups": [{"question": "This ruler defeated an invasion of a neighboring tribe, the Alemanni, at the Battle of Tolbiac. This man\u2019s wife Clotilde famously convinced him to convert to Christianity, after which he convened the First Council of Orleans. In his later rule, this chieftain proclaimed the Lex Salica to govern territory that he previously had secured in the 486 Battle of Soissons. For the point, name this Frankish king, considered the founder of the Merovingian Dynasty.", "answer": "<b> Clovis</b> I", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This battle led John Magruder to be sacked, even though he had successfully launched a diversionary attack at Beaver Dam Creek. This battle, which culminated with an engagement at Malvern Hill, was immortalized in a political cartoon that depicted a commander watching via telescope on a ship\u2019s mast. George McClellan\u2019s indecisiveness during this battle allowed Robert E. Lee to repel his forces from Richmond, ending the Peninsula Campaign in Virginia. For the point, name this series of battles in 1862 in which the Confederates took the offensive for a week.", "answer": "<b> Seven Days</b> Battles", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Day and month required. A document named for this date attempted to curb the excessive privilege of the<em> szlachta</em> [shlock-tah] and was passed by the Sejm [same] parliament in 1793, inspiring the name of a Polish constitution. Another event on this date featured mass executions on Principe Pio Hill and was commemorated in a painting showing a lantern illuminating a man in a white shirt with hands raised above his head. A firing squad prepares to fire on, for the point, what date in 1808, as commemorated in a painting by Francisco Goya?", "answer": "<b> 3</b>rd of<b> May</b> (accept<b> May 3</b>rd Constitution; accept The<b> Third of May 1808</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "William Gosse named this place one year after Ernest Giles became the first European to see a similar location, the Olgas. This place was created when mountain ranges in the Amadeus Basin were uplifted during the Petermann Orogeny. The orientation of the sun at certain times of the day changes the color of this location, which has a prevalence of feldspar-rich arkose. It will be prohibited to climb this location beginning in October 2019 due to a decision made by this location\u2019s Aboriginal owners. For the point, name this sandstone formation in Australia.", "answer": "<b> Uluru</b> (accept<b> Ayers Rock</b>)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This man avoided a statute on term limits by having his wife Lurleen succeed him. Four years later, this man was severly injured after being shot five times by Arthur Bremer in an unsuccessful run for president. This man promised to \u201ctoss the gauntlet before the feet of tyranny\u201d prior to blocking two black students from entry to Foster Auditorium, an action called the \u201cStand in the Schoolhouse Door.\u201d For the point, name this Alabama governor known for his advocacy of \u201csegregation forever.\u201d", "answer": "George<b> Wallace</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "With his assistant Denis Papin, this scientist attempted to develop a gunpowder engine. This man, who invented a harmonic device whose constant rate of swinging allowed for accurate time, manufactured a telescope with which he discovered Titan. This inventor of the pendulum clock aimed to replace Descartes\u2019prevailing optical theories by publishing his<em> Treatise on Light</em>. For the point, name this Dutch scientist who explained the behavior of wave fronts in a namesake principle and names a probe that traveled to Saturn with the<em> Cassini</em> orbiter.", "answer": "Christiaan<b> Huygens</b>", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "On the sidelines of the Genoa Conference, this country and its eastern neighbor signed a secret pact for military cooperation. This country\u2019s relations with Western Europe were normalized in the Locarno Treaties, although the \u201cstab-in-the-back\u201d myth continued to persist in this country, stemming from anger at the Treaty of Versailles. For the point, name this country that suffered extreme hyperinflation during the Weimar [vye-mar] Republic between losing the two World Wars.", "answer": "<b> Germany</b> (accept<b> Weimar</b> Republic before mentioned; do not accept German Empire)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This event was precipitated by the beating of missionary Marcella Sherwood. The Hunter Commission led the perpetrator of this event to be removed from his post, despite his claim that he upheld the Rowlatt Act\u2019s ban on mass gatherings. During this event, civilians celebrated the Baisakhi festival before they were fired on by Reginald Dyer\u2019s troops. Rabindranath Tagore renounced his knighthood in protest of, for the point, what 1919 massacre of hundreds of Indians in a garden near the Golden Temple in Sikhism\u2019s holiest city?", "answer": "<b> Jallianwala Bagh</b> massacre (accept 1919<b> Amritsar</b> massacre; do not accept Golden Temple massacre)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man resigned his Senate seat to Daniel Huger, but regained it after Huger resigned it as well. This first head of the Bureau of Indian Affairs faced an uproar when his wife Floride refused to speak with the adulterous wife of the Secretary of State, Peggy Eaton. This man responded to the Tariff of Abominations with the South Carolina Exposition and Protest. For the point, name this voice of nullification, a member of the \u201cGreat Triumvirate\u201d along with Clay and Webster.", "answer": "John<b> Calhoun</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A location in Rajam\u00a8aki belonging to Alko became a major producer of these weapons. Potassium chlorate was one of the ingredients used to make these weapons, which share a name with cluster bombs that became known as \u201cbread baskets.\u201d Over 450,000 of these weapons were produced during the Winter War, in which they were often manufactured alongside matches. A foreign minister of Russia during World War II names, for the point, what makeshift explosive commonly created from a flaming rag and a bottle of alcohol?", "answer": "<b> Molotov cocktail</b>s", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Manuel Lisa built a fort on this river\u2019s confluence with the Yellowstone River. John Evans explored this river and made an early map of it that was used by a group that met the Mandans along it. The Black Eagle Dam in Great Falls, Montana became the first dam on this river in 1890. The Corps of Discovery was guided by Sacagawea and led by Lewis and Clark, the first Europeans to travel the length of, for the point, what river that empties into the Mississippi River near St. Louis?", "answer": "<b> Missouri</b> River", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s friendship with Erhard Milch prevented him from resigning his posts after suffering an inflamed knee. After Fritz Todt was killed in an aviation accident, this man was forced to become the Minister of Armaments. This man, who used 152 anti-aircraft searchlights to create his famous \u201cCathedral of Light\u201d effect, wrote the book<em> Inside the Third Reich</em> detailing his time as the \u201cNazi who said sorry.\u201dFor the point, name this chief architect for Nazi Germany.", "answer": "Albert<b> Speer</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man rose to prominence after convincing the Union League Club to support John Hoffmann. Richard Connolly\u2019s management of financial records helped protect this man, though he lost popularity after the Orange Riots broke out. This man was thrown into the Ludlow Street Jail, where he died in 1878. This man\u2019s face was depicted as a sack of money by cartoonist Thomas Nast, who helped convict him of embezzlement. For the point, name this infamous head of New York\u2019s Tammany Hall political machine.", "answer": "William Magear \u201cBoss\u201d<b> Tweed</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "The Chanyu Modu defeated this dynasty at the Battle of Baideng, forcing this dynasty to accept marriage alliances called Heqin [he-chin]. The Revolt of the Seven States occurred during this dynasty, which was founded by a man who avoided assassination at the Feast at the Hong Gate. Rising over the Chu under Xiang Yu [shee-ang yu], this dynasty was usurped by Wang Mang. Founded by Liu Bang, this dynasty fell during the Yellow Turban Revolt. For the point, name this dynasty immediately following the Qin [chin] that names the largest ethnic group in China.", "answer": "<b> Han</b> Dynasty", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This policy was carried out by an newly-created administration led by Edward Stettinius and later Leo Crowley. This policy was enacted shortly after a declaration that a leader saw his country as a \u201cgreat arsenal of democracy.\u201d This policy, which was compared to allowing a neighbor to use your garden hose during a fire, officially ended America\u2019s neutral stance during World War II. For the point, name this policy that sought to aid Allied countries through shipments of weaponry and food.", "answer": "<b> Lend-Lease</b> Act", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Despite three affidavits providing evidence of this product\u2019s existence, the European Union stripped this product of its trademark in Europe in 2019. American gold medals in the 1984 Olympics earned consumers this product, which backfired after the Soviet boycott improved Team USA\u2019s performance. Since 1986,<em> The Economist</em> has maintained a currency comparison index named for this product. In 1967, Jim Delligatti invented, for the point, what fast food item with \u201ctwo all-beef patties and special sauce,\u201dsold by McDonalds?", "answer": "<b> Big Mac</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This man paid the Alvsborg Ransom to bring an end to the Kalmar War. At the Battle of the Rain, this man crossed the Lech River to defeat Count Tilly. Axel Oxenstierna ruled as chancellor after this man was slain leading cavalry at Lutzen against imperial forces. This man was immortalized as the \u201cLion of the North\u201d after a 1630 intervention to aid Protestants in Germany. For the point, name this Swedish king who entered the Thirty Years\u2019 War.", "answer": "<b> Gustavus Adolphus</b> (accept<b> Gustav II</b> Adolf; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A Day of Remembrance for this class of people is held annually on November 20th in honor of Rita Hester and others. After a TV writer controversially asked the British National Lottery to review a charity supporting this cause, Harry Brewis hosted Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez and other activists during a 57-hour Twitch livestream of<em> Donkey Kong 64</em> that raised $340,000 for that charity. The charity Mermaids UK raises awareness for, for the point, what people with a personal identity different to that of their assigned sex, the \u201cT\u201d in LGBT?", "answer": "<b> trans</b>gender/transsexual activism (accept anything related to promoting equal rights and/or support for<b> trans</b>gender and/or transsexual people; prompt on \u201cyouth activism\u201d after \u201cTV writer\u201d is read; prompt on anti-suicide/anti-self harm activism)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "During this conflict, William Shepherd ordered his troops to fire grape shot at a crowd of gathered Regulators. A militia funded by James Bowdoin and led by Benjamin Lincoln tried to suppress this conflict. George Washington returned from retirement in response to this conflict, whose leader failed to seize the Springfield armory despite rallying thousands in protest of unfair taxes. For the point, name this unsuccessful 1787 rebellion in Massachusetts which exposed the flaws of the Articles of Confederation.", "answer": "<b> Shays\u2019</b> Rebellion (or Uprising, etc.; do not accept or prompt on \u201cShay\u201d alone)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This poem, whose title entity \u201cshall sweep the clouds no more,\u201d was inspired by an 1830 article in the<em> Boston Daily Advertiser</em>. \u201cHarpies of the shore shall pluck\u201d at the title vessel of this poem, whose\u201cthunders shook the mighty deep\u201d and which had a \u201cdeck, once red with heroes\u2019 blood\u201d and a \u201choly flag\u201d\u201cNailed to her mast.\u201d A call to \u201ctear her tattered ensign down\u201d opens, for the point, what Oliver Wendell Holmes poem commemorating a ship that fought the<em> HMS Guerriere</em>, the<em> USS Constitution</em>?", "answer": "<b> Old Ironsides</b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Poetry"}, {"question": "For his work promoting this entity, Cyrus Avery is sometimes known as the \u201cFather\u201d of it. The lyric\u201cWon\u2019t you get hip to this timely tip\u201d is from a Bobby Troup song about this entity. The Green Book found that African-Americans were only able to stay in 6 percent of motels along this feature, which was called the \u201cmother road\u201d by John Steinbeck in<em> The Grapes of Wrath</em>. Chicago and Santa Monica were the original terminals of, for the point, what iconic American road that opened in 1926?", "answer": "U.S.<b> Route 66</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s economic \u201cshock therapy\u201d was derided by Alexander Rutskoy as suicide and helped prompt Parliament into revolt. After becoming president, this man acted as the most prominent signatory to the Belavezha Accords and entered his country into the CIS. This man gave a speech atop a tank to thwart the coup of the Gang of Eight before taking power, and he resigned in 1999 amidst problems with alcoholism. For the point, name this first leader of the Russian Federation.", "answer": "Boris<b> Yeltsin</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}